<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Upon the marriage of Prince George of Denmark with the Lady Anne: And his being install'd Knight of the Garter. A Pindarick poem.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06378</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 13306751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 806.k.16[114]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12408</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99882708</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99882708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06378)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:1[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Upon the marriage of Prince George of Denmark with the Lady Anne: And his being install'd Knight of the Garter. A Pindarick poem.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>George, --  Prince, consort of Anne, Queen of Great Britain, 1653-1708 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anne, --  Queen of Great Britain, 1665-1714 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Epithalamia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->
            <head>UPON THE MARRIAGE OF <hi>Prince George of Denmark</hi> WITH THE LADY ANNE: And his being Inſtall'd Knight of the Garter.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Pindarick POEM.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t gaudent pater AEneas &amp; avunculus Hector.</l>
               </q>
               <bibl>Virg.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>ALmighty Love! who can thy Ways define?</l>
               <l>Thou ſmall Intreaguing God, thou'rt all Deſign;</l>
               <l>Thy Quiver and thy Darts are farther known</l>
               <l>Than the gay wandring Bow w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in the Clouds is ſhewn;</l>
               <l>Thou keep'ſt the Gods themſelves in awe</l>
               <l>By thy Univerſal Law.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove,</hi> though amidſt his ſtores of Rain and Hail,</l>
               <l>Againſt thy Secret Flames can nought prevail;</l>
               <l>Thou breakeſt through his Guards, and with thy Dart</l>
               <l>Doſt pierce the groaning Monarch to the Heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:181720:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
                  <hi>Neptune,</hi> though all around with Waves oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Yet by the Ocean finds his Love increaſt,</l>
               <l>Like Water which on Fire's caſt.</l>
               <l>Nay, thou beyond the Tropicks canſt approach,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Sol</hi> in all his Journey dare not touch,</l>
               <l>Let it be Torrid, or the Frigid Zone,</l>
               <l>There an Empire thou doſt own,</l>
               <l>Which wou'd both Temperate be,</l>
               <l>Were it not, bold God, for Thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Denmark,</hi> which lies remoter from the Sun,</l>
               <l>With as brisk Flames, we find, as <hi>Britain</hi> burn:</l>
               <l>Thou firſt didſt fire the Prince's Heart,</l>
               <l>Then to Her Breaſt the Meſſage ſtreight impart;</l>
               <l>He own'd thy Power, and never ſtay'd,</l>
               <l>But thy Godſhip ſoon obey'd:</l>
               <l>Led by thy Light through rowling Seas he mov'd</l>
               <l>To meet his Royal Love.</l>
               <l>He fear'd no Rocks that lay between,</l>
               <l>So that within her Breaſt none cou'd be ſeen.</l>
               <l>He fear'd not what from Seas and Winds cou'd come,</l>
               <l>So that her Breath did not pronounce his fatal Doom.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Veſta</hi>'s Flame it ſelf did once maintain</l>
               <l>Through the black Deep, till it the Port did gain,</l>
               <l>Till it at <hi>Rome</hi> had reach'd the Sacred Fane.</l>
               <l>Nor did he long expect his Doom,</l>
               <l>He did but <hi>Come,</hi> and <hi>See,</hi> and <hi>Overcome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By Parlee and Capitulation</l>
               <l>In ten days ſpace her Virgin Fort he wone.</l>
               <l>An eaſier Conqueſt <hi>Jove</hi> cou'd never boaſt,</l>
               <l>No Miſtreſs ever ſtood him in leſs coſt,</l>
               <l>When Cloiſter'd <hi>Danae</hi> he wou'd gain,</l>
               <l>To bribe her Keepers he was fain;</l>
               <l>With Gold his Godſhip then was forc'd to buy</l>
               <l>New Morſels and Supplies for his Almighty Luxury.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Pardon, Bleſt Pair, theſe rude unpoliſht Lines,</l>
               <l>With which a Loyal Muſe wou'd now approach your Shrines;</l>
               <l>Like ſome young Virgin, who when half undreſt,</l>
               <l>(Around her looſely caſt her Veſt)</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:181720:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
               <l>Into the Croud with eager ſteps does goe</l>
               <l>To gaze and wonder at the pompous Show.</l>
               <l>Wellcome, Great Prince, to our <hi>Once</hi> happy Shore</l>
               <l>(For this one time, dear Land, thy pardon I implore)</l>
               <l>For many years the Pride of all the Floud,</l>
               <l>The Envy of the Weſtern World it ſtood;</l>
               <l>In this our Iſle, as once of <hi>Rhodes</hi> was ſaid,</l>
               <l>The Sun was never thought to hide his Head:</l>
               <l>Antiquity with all its ſearching eyes,</l>
               <l>Cou'd never fancy or deviſe,</l>
               <l>That once in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or in <hi>Albion</hi> Clouds cou'd riſe.</l>
               <l>Let Fortunate or Happy now no longer be its name,</l>
               <l>But ſtyle it henceforth <hi>Europe</hi>'s ſhame:</l>
               <l>As in Greek Story, we of Countreys reade,</l>
               <l>That for their Sins have often chang'd their Breed;</l>
               <l>Of Men or Manners, ſo, no more appears,</l>
               <l>But all are here transform'd to Lions, Dogs and Bears</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>But the Miſtaken World may fancy yet</l>
               <l>That Happineſs here keeps her peacefull Seat,</l>
               <l>Who ſee our thronged Streets ſtill ebb and flow</l>
               <l>With Waves of people crowding to and fro;</l>
               <l>Who with ſuch artfull beauty and ſurpriſe</l>
               <l>See all our Palaces and Temples riſe,</l>
               <l>Who ſee our Navies daily plow the Main,</l>
               <l>With a full Harveſt bleſt of dear-bought gain;</l>
               <l>Some fraighted with the Golden Spoils o'th' Weſt,</l>
               <l>Some with the ſhining Entrails of the Eaſt:</l>
               <l>So a poor Swain viewing a Tyrant's ſtate,</l>
               <l>With ſecret envy does applaud his fate,</l>
               <l>But yet ne'er learns to prize his own dear peacefull Reſt,</l>
               <l>Nor ſees thoſe inward flames that wrack the gaudy Pageant's Breaſt.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Aetna</hi> to the diſtant Sailers fight.</l>
               <l>Shews with a Top that's verdant, flouriſhing and bright,</l>
               <l>But yet within its burning Womb contains</l>
               <l>Nothing but Brimſtone, Lime, and ſcorching ſulphurous Veins.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:181720:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Yet from theſe Miſts, Great Sir, that darken all the Air</l>
               <l>A ſudden Joy does dart, and ſcatter our deſpair,</l>
               <l>When thus by you a way we open'd find</l>
               <l>How the Fates may ſtill be kind,</l>
               <l>How by your Royal Progeny</l>
               <l>We and our Sons may ever happy be.</l>
               <l>So have I ſeen a kind auſpicious Star</l>
               <l>Shine forth, and guide the wandring Traveller,</l>
               <l>While all elſe ſtood with thickeſt Night beſet,</l>
               <l>This ſparkled like a Diamond ſet in Jet.</l>
               <l>So from two warring Clouds black teeming Womb</l>
               <l>Oft have I ſeen the frisking Lightning come,</l>
               <l>And trembling run o'er all the Azure way,</l>
               <l>And with its Light create a ſhort-liv'd Day.</l>
               <l>Th'unruly Many now ſhall ceaſe to rage,</l>
               <l>Or ever more diſturb the Age.</l>
               <l>No more ſhall <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and bold <hi>Anarchy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Among our Engliſh Manufactures numbred be;</l>
               <l>Pale <hi>Faction</hi> now ſhall hang its drooping head,</l>
               <l>It ſhall be through the World expreſt</l>
               <l>That Oracles are once more ceas'd,</l>
               <l>That the <hi>Old Cauſe,</hi> the mighty <hi>Pan</hi> is dead.</l>
               <l>Theſe curſt heart-burnings and ill-boding Flames</l>
               <l>Shall hence be exorcis'd by your Illuſtrious Name,</l>
               <l>As Culinary Fire,</l>
               <l>In the Sun's beams does loſe its force; and ſtreight expire.</l>
               <l>The giddy Rabble, and the Beaſts of Prey,</l>
               <l>Shall by your Nuptial Fires be ſcar'd away,</l>
               <l>As men in <hi>Africa</hi> do Bonfires rear,</l>
               <l>To keep 'em from the Lion and the Savage Bear.</l>
               <l>Then let our Brittiſh Annals talk no more</l>
               <l>Of one St. <hi>George,</hi> his Deeds, and wondrous Power,</l>
               <l>This is the Man; him the Great <hi>ORDER</hi> ſhall</l>
               <l>In future times their Saint and Patron call,</l>
               <l>And what before was Legend, Fable, Lie,</l>
               <l>Shall paſs for current and Authentick Hiſtory.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Davis.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
